is לו Lamed Vav 36. Okay and we pick up at the
middle or no not the middle the bottom of לה עמוד ב
Lamed Hey amud Bet and we're dealing with a whole debate about
about some details about the stones. Now I do want to say
by the way correction of what I said yesterday. I went back
back and I've truly read the פסוקים psukim a little bit more
carefully and it's important also in terms of understanding what the גמרא
Gemara is about to do.
The גמרא Gemara said there were three stones sets of stones. Those
that משה Moshe erected on his side of the ירדן Yarden which
is not in the פסוקים psukim but the גמרא Gemara learns גזירה
שוה gzeira shava באר באר, be'er be'er, the stones in the ירדן
Yarden and then it speaks about
the stones that they took out of the ירדן Yarden and you
know and erected in גלגל Gilgal and we'll talk about those and
wrote the תורה Torah on them etc. Now the the ones that
they erected in the ירדן Yarden were not the same ones that
they took out of the ירדן Yarden and then erected in גלגל.
Gilgal. The פסוקים psukim actually say explicitly that וישאם שם עד היום
הזה, Vayusham sham ad hayom hazeh, you know so they were erected
in the ירדן Yarden nobody sees them so they were I guess
the act of erecting them was symbolic, the knowledge that they were
there was symbolic but nobody actually gets to see them. Those remained
in the ירדן Yarden and a different 12 they took out. Now
there's two things that happen. There's the erecting of the stones in
גלגל Gilgal and then there is the there is the writing of
the תורה. Torah. Now actually on the stones. Now if you actually
look at the פסוקים psukim in in the תורה Torah here in
דברים כז Devarim Kaf Zayin it says the following. Yeah it says
so it has all the ברכות brachos and the קללות klalos and
it says like this: והיה ביום אשר תעברו את הירדן אל הארץ
אשר ה׳ אלהיך נתן לך והקמת לך אבנים גדלות ושדת אתם בשיד.
Ve-hayah bayom asher tavru et ha-Yarden el ha-aretz asher Hashem Elokecha noten
lach ve-hakemota le-cha avanim gedolot ve-sata otam ba-sid. So there you've got
the
stones and
the plaster. No mention that they came from the ירדן Yarden but
okay they they could be those stones. Anyways so you erect these
big stones וכתבת עליהן את כל דברי התורה הזאת בעברך למען אשר
תבא אל הארץ אשר ה׳ אלהיך נתן לך ארץ זבת חלב ודבש
אשר דבר ה׳ אלהי אבתיך לך. Ve-katavta aleihen et kol divrei ha-Torah
ha-zot be-ovrecha le-maan asher tavo el ha-aretz asher Hashem Elokecha noten lach
eretz zavat chalav u-devash asher diber Hashem Elokei avotecha lach. Okay so
it sounds like you write them on these stones that you were
erecting. והיה בעברכם את הירדן תקימו את האבנים האלה אשר אנכי מצוה
אתכם היום בהר עיבל ושדת אותם בשיד. Ve-hayah be-ovrechem et ha-Yarden takimu
et ha-avanim ha-eleh asher anochi metzaveh etchem hayom be-Har Eival ve-sata otam
ba-sid. So these stones where do they get put? They put at
הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har Eival. ובנית שם מזבח
לה׳ אלהיך מזבח אבנים לא תניף עליהם ברזל. U-vanita sham mizbeiach l'Hashem
Elokecha mizbach avanim lo tanif aleihem barzel. אבנים שלמות תבנה את מזבח
ה׳ אלהיך והעלית עליו עולות לה׳ אלהיך. Avanim shelemot tivneh et mizbach
Hashem Elokecha ve-haalita alav olot l'Hashem Elokecha. וזבחת שלמים ואכלת שם ושמחת
לפני ה׳ אלהיך. Ve-zavachta shelamim ve-achalta sham ve-samachta lifnei Hashem Elokecha. So
so far it sounds like the
stones are erected at הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har
Eival. It said before that you write on them right וכתבת עליהן
את כל דברי התורה. ve-chatavta aleihen et kol divrei ha-Torah. Then it
says you erect these stones and you build a מזבח. mizbeiach. And
then right it says it twice you basically erect these stones and
so you erect these stones and you write on them and then
it says you build a מזבח mizbeiach with אבנים שלמות avanim shelemot
and then it says you write on the אבנים avanim את דברי
התורה הזאת באר היטב. et divrei ha-Torah ha-zot ba'er hetev. So are
we going back to the אבנים avanim that are erected or the
אבני המזבח? avnei hamizbeiach? So so if you so it's confusing.
The other thing is is that what happened when they crossed the
ירדן? Yarden? Okay so let's stop there it's confusing. So take a
look for a second at תוספות Tosafot כיצד כתבו ישראל את התורה.
Keitzad katvu
Yisrael et
ha-Torah. The תוספות Tosafot on לה עמוד ב. Lamed Hey amud Bet.
בתוספתא be-Tosefta רבי יהודה אומר על גבי המזבח כתבוה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
al gabi hamizbeiach katvuha. Okay so he basically reads that the אבנים
avanim somehow were were were they the same? Did they then use
those stones to build the מזבח? mizbeiach? Or no they you know
no they did
erect stones but the writing was on the מזבח
mizbeiach but the פסוקים psukim are ambiguous. Okay על גבי מזבח כתבוה.
Al gabi mizbeiach katvuha. אבל בירושלמי תני Aval bi-Yerushalmi tani על אבני
המלון נכתבו al avnei hamalon nichtevu כדברי רבי יהודה. ki-v'rei Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יוסי אומר על אבני מזבח נכתבו. Rabbi Yosi omer al avnei
mizbeiach nichtevu. מן דאמר אבני מלון בכל יום ויום אומות העולם היו
משלחין נוטרין ומסין את התורה שהייתה כתובה בשבעים לשון. Man d'amar avnei
malon be-chol yom va-yom umot ha-olam hayu mishalchin notrin u-masin et ha-Torah
she-hayta ketuva be-shiv'im lashon. So fine then they were there the written
תורה Torah was a monument on these stones and that could be
the non-Jews could send their scribes and they could transcribe it. מן
דאמר אבני מזבח לא לשעה היו ונגנזו. Man d'amar avnei mizbeiach lo
le-sha'ah hayu ve-nignazu. So no what do you do? I mean presumably
if it's just a מזבח mizbeiach you don't have something written on
a מזבח mizbeiach that's going to serve both as a monument. I
don't know why. Why don't you also writing on a מזבח mizbeiach
might as well use it as both. But anyway the גמרא Gemara
says no מה עשיתי נתן הקדוש ברוך הוא בינה בלב כל אומה
ואומה והשיאו את התורה שהייתה כתובה בשבעים לשון. Ma asiti natan Hakadosh
Baruch Hu bina be-lev kol uma va-uma ve-hasiu et ha-Torah she-hayta ketuva
be-shiv'im lashon. Somehow no they maybe they transcribed it as well, not
exactly clear. But anyway מן דאמר על אבני מלון נכתבו Man d'amar
al avnei malon nichtevu ניחא ושדת אותם בשיד nicha ve-sata otam ba-sid
אלא מן דאמר על אבני מזבח נכתבו מאי ושדת אותם? ela man
d'amar al avnei mizbeiach nichtevu mai ve-sata otam? Where is the plaster?
בין כל אבן ואבן. Bein kol even va-even. No, it means the
plaster that's holding the stones together. Okay so there's this ambiguity that
the תורה Torah speaks about erecting stones
and building a מזבח mizbeiach and the first issue is Now the
other thing that you need to deal with is what did they
actually do in יהושע? Yehoshua? Because in where did they write the
תורה? Torah? Because if you take a look at a map, okay,
I went to try to look at the map again exactly see
where's גלגל, Gilgal, which is where they rested after they crossed the
ירדן, Yarden, right, that's the מלון. Malon. And then there's הר גריזים
Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har Eival. So first of all,
I typed in to Google because you know because גלגל Gilgal nobody
knows exactly where גלגל Gilgal is. But it seems from the פסוקים
Pesukim it's right near יריחו. Yericho. So I typed in like, you
know, to Google Maps, you know, Jericho Israel, and it gave me
some Jericho Junction in Jerusalem. So I tried it in Hebrew, you
know, יריחו ישראל Yericho Yisrael and it also gave me some Jericho
Junction. So I went back to I went to Wikipedia to look
for it, and they had a map, and it said, location of
גלגל Gilgal or יריחו, Yericho, you know, comma Palestine. So like I
got really upset, like I was saying like what, have they become
like anti-semites, Google here, whatever, but then I realized like actually no,
we actually gave יריחו. Yericho. So actually it should have said Palestinian
Authority, not Palestine. Anyways, I went back to Google and then I
typed in יריחו Yericho Palestine and then it showed me where it
was exactly on the map. Anyway, so I looked at a map,
sort of the location of יריחו Yericho relative to הר גריזים Har
Gerizim and הר עיבל, Har Eival, and if you take a look,
right, יריחו's Yericho pretty much like right, you know, right at like
the edge of the Dead Sea or whatever, it's right after you
cross over the Jordan. And הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל
Har Eival is way far away, you know, אחרי דרך מבוא השמש.
Acharei Derech Mevo HaShemesh. I mean the גמרא Gemara says like sixty
to how many פרסות Parsot the גמרא Gemara said, it's a couple
days' journey, okay. Now, and the פסוקים Pesukim say that they crossed
over and they slept at night and they erected the stones that
night, right. So you would think that these are going to be
different things. If you have the stones and you erect them and
you write the תורה Torah on them, and the you know but
the תורה Torah sort of has it all sort of come together
at הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har Eival. The תורה
Torah doesn't have two stages, okay. So if you take a look
at what it says in יהושע, Yehoshua, it says like this: והעם
עלו מן הירדן בעשור לחדש הראשון ויחנו בגלגל בקצה מזרח יריחו. Ve'ha'am
alu min ha'Yarden b'asor lachodesh harishon vayachanu ba'Gilgal biktzeh mizrach Yericho. Okay,
in the right at the edge of יריחו's Yericho גלגל. Gilgal. ואת
שתים עשרה האבנים האלה אשר לקחו מן הירדן הקים יהושע בגלגל. Ve'et
shtem esrei ha'avanim ha'eleh asher laku min ha'Yarden hekim Yehoshua ba'Gilgal. Okay,
he erected them, okay, with no writing of the תורה, Torah, he
just erected them, okay. אשר ישאלון בניכם מחר לאמר מה האבנים האלה
והודעתם את בניכם לאמר ביבשה עבר ישראל את הירדן הזה אשר הוביש
השם אלקיכם את מי הירדן מפניכם Asher yishalun bneichem machar lemor ma
ha'avanim ha'eleh vehodatem et bneichem lemor beyabasha avar Yisrael et ha'Yarden hazeh
asher hovish Hashem Elokeichem et mei ha'Yarden mipneichem etc. etc. למען דעת
כל עמי הארץ כי יד השם כי חזקה היא למען יראתם את
השם אלקיכם כל הימים. Lema'an da'at kol amei ha'aretz ki yad Hashem
ki chazaka hi lema'an yiratem et Hashem Elokeichem kol hayamim. He just
erected the stones, no writing of the תורה, Torah, no building of
the מזבח Mizbei'ach by הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har
Eival. Then they go and they do the whole war with יריחו,
Yericho, יריחו סגרת ומסגרת, Yericho sogeret usugereth, they have a whole big
war, right, the whole thing with עכן Achan etc. and then, okay,
after all of that, then they do war again against העי, Ha'Ai,
I mean they have all these wars, and then finally in פרק
ח Perek Chet towards the end of פרק ח Perek Chet it
says the following: אז יבנה יהושע מזבח להשם אלקי ישראל בהר עיבל.
Az yivneh Yehoshua mizbei'ach l'Hashem Elokei Yisrael be'Har Eival. So after a
couple of those initial wars, then they finally got around to the
ברכות Brachos and the קללות Klalos of הר גריזים Har Gerizim and
הר עיבל. Har Eival. Until now the גמרא's Gemara been writing the
narrative, it sounded like first thing they did the day they crossed
over the ירדן Yarden was the ברכות Brachos and the קללות, Klalos,
right, but you read the narrative, no, actually it's quite distant into
the land, they had to fight a few wars first, okay, a
few battles, okay, then he builds the מזבח Mizbei'ach כאשר צוה משה
Moshe. עבד השם את בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael ככתוב בספר תורת משה
Moshe מזבח Mizbei'ach אבנים avanim שלמות אשר lo הניף עליהם ברזל ויעלו
עליו עלות להשם ויזבחו שלמים ויכתב שם על האבנים. And what stones
do you think it's talking about? Which they took from before? I
don't think so, this is three פרקים Perakim later after a lot
of wars, and it says they built the מזבח Mizbei'ach, אבנים שלמות
אשר לא הניף עליהם ברזל ויכתב שם על האבנים. avanim shlemot asher
lo henif aleihem barzel vayichtav sham al ha'avanim. It's three פרקים, Perakim,
we're not still talking about the אבנים avanim, that they were making
in גלגל, Gilgal, which they left in גלגל. Gilgal. They wrote it,
פשט pshat is, on the מזבח, Mizbei'ach right, on those אבנים, avanim
okay, משנה תורת משה אשר כתב לפני בני ישראל. mishneh Torat Moshe
asher katav lifnei bnei Yisrael. מאת האבנים. Me'eit ha'avanim. וכל ישראל וזקניו
ושטריו ושפטיו עמדים מזה ומזה לארון נגד הכהנים, V'chol Yisrael uzkeinav v'shotrav
v'shoftav omdim mizeh umizeh la'aron neged hakohanim, they stood and they did
הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל Har Eival and then they
did the whole ברכות Brachos and קללות, Klalos, okay, ואחרי כן קרא,
ve'acharei chen kara, yeah, it says וחציו אל מול עיבל כאשר צוה
משה עבד השם לברך את עם ישראל בראשונה ואחרי כן קרא את
כל דברי התורה הברכה והקללה ככל הכתוב בספר התורה. ve'chetzyo el mul
Eival ka'asher tziva Moshe eved Hashem l'varech et am Yisrael barishona ve'acharei
chen kara et kol divrei ha'Torah habracha ve'haklalala kechol hakatuv b'sefer ha'Torah.
לא היה דבר מכל אשר צוה משה אשר לא קרא יהושע נגד
כל קהל ישראל והנשים והטף והגר ההלך בקרבם. Lo haya davar mikol
asher tziva Moshe asher lo kara Yehoshua neged kol kehal Yisrael vehanashim
vehataf vehager haholech bekirbam. Okay, so it sounds like actually, it's bizarre,
but it's actually there was already an ambiguity
in
the פסוקים, Pesukim, and it sounds like this real separation of these
two events, right? There's the הקמת אבנים hakamat avanim which was not
the writing of the תורה, Torah, then there was weeks later, I
don't know, months later, it sounds like הר גריזים, הר עיבל Har
Gerizim Har Eival much
more interior in the land, right, with a מזבח Mizbei'ach. and presumably
the תורה's Torah on the מזבח. mizbeach, The תורה Torah is sort
of, the גמרא Gemara is sort of trying to pull it all
together, right, and And so on the one hand, the stones that
יהושע Yehoshua erects becomes the stones that the תורה Torah is written
on,
the
stones
that he took out of the ירדן Yarden in the גלגל, Gilgal,
and there's also this somehow sense that the ברכות brachot and the
קללות klalot were sort of like right then, right? So somehow I
don't know what they, how they bracket all of them. Maybe they
just sort of bracket those battles. Those battles occurred later, not at
that time. You know, they sort of אין מוקדם ומאוחר Ein Mukdam
Umeuchar or something. Anyway, but like they erect these stones in
גלגל, Gilgal, they do the ברכות brachos and the קללות, klalos, and
then they maybe use
those stones at הר גריזים Har Gerizim, and הר עיבל, Har Eival
you know, to write the תורה Torah on it, right? Somehow some
way of like conflating these two things. I probably now have confused
you all very thoroughly. But, but you know, it's in the, it's
in the narrative it's clear. There're
the stones which
are erected which are not the writing of the תורה. Torah. There's
many weeks later the building of the מזבח, mizbeach.
the ברכות brachos and the קללות, klalos, that sounds like the
תורה Torah is written on them, stones of the
מזבח. mizbeach. The גמרא Gemara somehow tries to bring it all together
and make it maybe all at the same day essentially and we'll
see more about that, and have the writing of the תורה Torah
more on the stones that they took out of the ירדן Yarden
than on the מזבח. mizbeach, Yes. Okay, yeah. You want, well when
I was giving this, you know, דף Daf summary away, what I
mentioned was the מלבים Malbim and who
basically says, especially if you look at the פסוקים, psukim, are you
doing the plastering before or after the whole thing? Right. So he
says that there actually was two times that this, and you know
sort of like אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים Eilu V'Eilu Divrei Elokim
Chayim and that on the one hand, first you wrote it when
it was the plaster was just beginning to dry because you know
that you can still write in it. And then, you know, so
that's what they did in the ירדן. Yarden. Then they took all,
took these stones and then they started building the מזבח, mizbe'ach, do
the
עולות, olot, and you know they plastered again as all that was
going on. Plaster dried out a little bit, they wrote it yet
again. The reason why they did that was because you know otherwise
they'd say I'm going to have to cut you off here. This
is a תורה Torah of the מלבים, Malbim, it's a little bit
too complicated. We need to do with a complexity that's actually here,
we don't need to add more complexity. So we'll have to do
that some other time. Okay, so anyway, fine. Okay, so back to
the גמרא. Gemara. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara now is, and
maybe should have held off that because we, anyway we'll just get
through wrapping up the point and then we'll come right back to
the point that I said, which was the גמרא's Gemara dealing with
this debate about רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda and רבי שמעון Reb Shimon
about how much was it that had the other nations done תשובה
teshuvah they would have been accepted? And what does it mean accepted?
Does it mean accepted as גרים? gerim? Does it mean anyway what
does the other nations mean? It sounds from context it means the
כנענים Canaanite nations that were living outside of Israel. Had they, you
know, did they have an option of not being wiped out if
the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael, were to ever go to war against
them, would the מצווה mitzvah of destroying the שבעת עממים seven nations
apply even outside of Israel? Okay, so we'll pick up where at
the very bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב' lamed heh amud bais and
the following. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי טעמא Mai
taama let's pick up with אמר רבא amar Rava six lines from
the bottom. אמר רבא בר שילא Amar Rava bar Shila מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון? mai taama d'Reb Shimon? דכתיב Dechtiv there's that רבי שמעון
Reb Shimon that says that had they learned they would have been
accepted. דכתיב והיו עמים משרפות שיד על עסקי שיד. Dechtiv vehayu amim
misrofos sid al iskei sid. So that they the will be the
the conflagration of plaster because of the plaster. They should have learned
from the what was written on the plaster and then they wouldn't
be destroyed. רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda, כשיד, kesid, no, just like plaster.
מה שיד אין לו תקנה Ma sid ein lo takanah the same
way plaster has no will ultimately be I guess destroyed אלא שריפה
ella sereifah אף אותם הכותים הגוים אין להם תקנה אלא שריפה. af
osam hakutim hagoyim ein lahem takanah ella sereifah. תמן אזלה הא דתניא
T'man azla ha detanya ושבית שביו veshavisa shivyo you'll capture your captive
by the יפת תואר yefas to'ar לרבות lirabos כנענים Canaanim it's probably
גוים Goyim is probably the גרסא girsa that you have, right? Probably
anyway, no, כנענים Canaanim actually כנענים Canaanim makes sense here. I take
it back. Actually דווקא davka here it should be כנענים. Canaanim. Right.
Because we're dealing exactly with the שבעת עממים shivas ummim issue. לרבות
כנענים שבחוץ לארץ Lirabos Canaanim shebechutz la'aretz that even the כנענים Canaanites
outside if אם חוזרין בתשובה מקבלין אותם im chozrin bitshuvah mekabelin osam
that if they were to do תשובה teshuvah they could be accepted.
So כמאן? keman? דרבי שמעון. D'Reb Shimon. That's like רבי שמעון Reb
Shimon because רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says that were they to do
תשובה teshuvah right we would not have to destroy them were we
to go in war and find the שבעת עממים shivas ammim outside,
whereas רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda is understood to say no the שבעת
עממים shivas ammim even regardless have to be destroyed everywhere even outside
of Israel even if they do תשובה. teshuvah. Now תוספות Tosafos has
two very brief points and then we're going to get back to
the whole יהושע Yehoshua narrative. תוספות Tosafos לרבות כנענים שבחוץ לארץ lirabos
Canaanim shebechutz la'aretz if you take a look תוספות Tosafos says תימה
היך קיבלו לה לרחב teima heich kibelu la l'Rachav שהרי היא הייתה
מכנען שבתוכה sheharei hi hayesa miCanaan shebechocha כדאיתא בספרי. kedi'isa b'Sifri. Okay,
and then תוספות Tosafos to answer this says what answer is if
you go look like five four lines before the lines get to
be the medium size where there's an asterisk it says ואי הוי
מצינן למימר ve'ee havai matzinan leimar and somehow the גרסא girsa מיהו
מצינן למימר mihu matzinan leimar דאם היו חוזרין אז בתשובה בשעה שכתב
את התורה d'im hayu chozrin az bitshuvah besha'ah shekasav es haTorah אפילו
כנענים שבתוכה היו מקבלין. afilu Canaanim shebechocha hayu mekabelin. ואפילו לרבי יהודה.
Va'afilu l'Reb Yehuda. He says when did they do תשובה? teshuvah? Did
they do תשובה teshuvah again whether תשובה teshuvah means they decided that
they would be you know try to convert or תשובה teshuvah just
means they were to abandon their idolatry or whatever. תוספות Tosafos says
did you do it before the war started or after the war
started? So he says if you would have done it before the
war started and then it would have been sincere and it would
not just have been a way to you know because of course
you had the גבעונים Givonim or whatever that tricked. and weren't sincere,
so everybody would have said, if you would have done it before
the war started, even the Canaanites in Israel, we wouldn't have had
to, you know, wipe out. The whole point was after the war
started. That's where there's the debate, and you know, the debate then
focuses on the Canaanites outside of Israel. So that's the way תוספות
Tosfos deals with the רחב Rachav story, you know, you could also
ask about the, anyway, so that's like one interesting issue, like when
is it possible for them to have done תשובה, teshuvah, whatever תשובה
teshuvah means to be accepted, again, accepted just might mean not wiped
out, or does it mean actually convert? And you know, and how
to deal with the רחב Rachav story. The other interesting thing, top
of ל"ו עמוד א' Lamed Vav Amud Aleph about this thing about
the יפת תואר Yafas Toar that, you know, well if it's even
the Canaanites, so it seems that we don't have to wipe out
the Canaanites outside of Israel, and that's like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
תוספות Tosfos says, ואם תאמר דילמא ביפת תואר אפילו רבי יהודה מודה
דלא דברה תורה אלא כנגד יצר הרע והא והותר שאר נכריות דלחמש
מסיני דכנען פוגים בה הותרה אפילו כנענים שבחוץ לארץ. v'im tomar dilma
b'yafas toar afilu Rabbi Yehuda modeh d'lo dibra torah ela k'neged yetzer
hara v'ha v'hutar sh'ar nachriyos d'lach'mush misinai d'kna'an pogim ba hutra afilu
knanim sheb'chutz la'aretz. He says how do you know that this is
part of the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, right? Other prohibitions are waived for יפת תואר, Yafas Toar,
I mean she's not Jewish. תוספות Tosfos later says a כהן, Kohen,
even a כהן, Kohen, the גמרא Gemara says is מותר mutar ביפת
תואר, b'yafas toar, even though clearly it violates the laws of כהונה.
kehuna. Okay, so maybe it also overrides the issues relating to, you
know, to the שבע אומות. shiva umos. So he wants, so he
asks like, right? Good question, if we're talking about יפת תואר Yafas
Toar maybe the rules are different. Now, part of the answer could
be the rules of sex might be different in terms of prohibited
sex, but if there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy them, then, you
know, okay, sex is מותר mutar but doesn't mean you don't have
to destroy them. So תוספות Tosfos sort of more or less says
something like that, that no, if there was a מצוה mitzvah to
destroy them even outside of חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, then that would
not have been waived even for יפת תואר. Yafas Toar. Okay, so
some interesting debates about whether to what degree is there a מצוה
mitzvah to wipe out the שבע אומות shiva umos outside of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, even if they've done תשובה, teshuvah, would they be
accepted? How do you deal with the רחב Rachav story? And whether
the whole יפת תואר Yafas Toar could apply to the שבע אומות
shiva umos in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, or whether, you know, whether
the fact that יפת תואר Yafas Toar would be a basis for
an exception. יפת תואר Yafas Toar applying in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
No, it's outside. No, yeah, when you are outside the land. Okay,
and not only that, but according to תוספות, Tosfos, it's not only
that they wanted to, but יהושע Yehoshua was proactive in this going
to them and offering them a peace treaty. Right, that's true, yes,
correct. Okay, so now let's continue. Okay, so I should probably wrap
that up first.
But keeping in mind, going back now to the basic narrative about
the אבנים that
they erected in גלגל Gilgal and then the הר גריזים Har Gerizim
and the point that I, you know, the issue about whether what
happened in הר גריזים Har Gerizim הר עיבל Har Eival, is connected
to what's the stones in גלגל Gilgal or not. So remember what
I... we read some of the פסוקים, pesukim, they weren't connected. Let's
go back now to the גמרא's Gemara narrative. Okay, בא וראה, bo
re'eh, come and see, כמה נסים נעשו באותו היום, kama nisim na'asu
b'oso hayom, how many miracles were done on that day that they
crossed the Jordan. עברו ישראל את הירדן, avru Yisrael es haYarden, they
crossed the Jordan, ובאו להר גריזים ולהר עיבל u'ba'u l'Har Gerizim u'l'Har
Eival יותר מששים מיל, yosher mi'shishim mil, so right there the גמרא
Gemara is, right, going back to the point I opened
with, right,
in the פסוקים pesukim it's
like, you know, like I said, they first had to fight יריחו
Yericho and they had to fight העי, Ha'Ai, and it's clearly that
it did not, all those battles did not happen one day. The
תורה Torah clearly talks about, you know, many days, like even the
יריחו, Yericho, how many days it took till the walls came down
and so on. Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara is basically doing
is it's bracketing like those two פרקים prakim and jumping to the
narrative in פרק ח' perek ches in יהושע Yehoshua and saying it
happened on the same day. Okay, it's combining these two. And it
acknowledges that that's a pretty serious trip to get all the way
to הר גריזים והר עיבל. Har Gerizim v'Har Eival.
יותר מששים מיל, yosher mi'shishim mil, more than sixty מיל, mil, ואין
כל בריה
יכולה לעמוד בפניהם,
v'ein kol beryah
yechola
la'amod bifneihem, and nobody was able to stand up against, you know,
the might of בני ישראל, Yisrael וכל העומד בפניהם היה נתרז. v'chol
h'omed bifneihem haya nisraz. Again, bracketing יריחו Yericho and העי. Ha'Ai. What?
How much is a מיל? mil? A מיל mil is a good
question. A מיל mil is about a kilometer. Okay, so sixty kilometers
is about thirty-six miles. That's a whole nation. Yes. And it's parallel
to coming out of רעמסס Ramses and they go that distance from
around... oh, maybe. But that's still seven days. Oh no, from רעמסס
Ramses to סוכות Succos you mean. Oh, I don't know, maybe. I'd
have to look about how חז"ל Chazal explain, yeah, how they explain
what that distance was. Right, I'm not sure they emphasize... I don't
remember if they emphasize the distance from רעמסס Ramses to סוכות, Succos,
but that's an interesting point. Maybe there's some of that. That's an
interesting point. At one point would they jump this big distance in
a very short time? כמאן דשרי. k'manei sharim. Right, right. I understand.
Yeah, yeah, no, it's a good point. Yeah, yeah. Okay. ואין כל
בריה יכולה לעמוד בפניהם, v'ein kol beryah yechola la'amod bifneihem, and nobody
could stand and, you know, up against them. וכל העומד בפניהם היה
נתרז, v'chol h'omed bifneihem haya nisraz, and anybody who tried to stand
up against them, immediately they sort of like lost control of their
bowels. שנאמר ואת אימתי אשלח לפניך, shene'emar v'es emasi ashalach lefanecha, I
will send my fear in front of you, והמותי את כל העם,
v'hamoti es kol ha'am, and I will sort of disturb... and what
does רש"י Rashi say? רש"י Rashi says ומהומה v'hamomah is like to,
you know, stir up or something. Yeah, anyway. רש״י *Rashi* says, where's
רש״י *Rashi*? והמתי לשון מהומה וערבוב הגוף מה שבתוכו *vehamoti lashon mehumah
ve'irvuv haguf mah shebetocho*. It causes the inners to lose control, okay?
אשר תבוא בהם *asher tavo bahem*. ואמר *ve'amar* תפול עליהם אימתה ופחד
*tipol aleihem eimatah vafachad*, fear and trembling. עד יעבור עמך השם *ad
ya'avor amcha Hashem*, זו ביאה Biah ראשונה *zu bi'ah rishonah*. Now we're
going to sort of דרשן *darshen* the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*. עד יעבור
עמך השם *ad ya'avor amcha Hashem*, זו ביאה ראשונה *zu bi'ah rishonah*,
the first time they entered in the time of יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*.
עד יעבור עם זו קנית *ad ya'avor am zu kanita*, the end
of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* which is obviously just poetic parallel, this
nation that you acquired, זו ביאה שנייה *zu bi'ah sheniyah*, that's the
second entering into the land. אמרו מעתה ראויים היו ישראל Yisrael לעשות
להם נס בביאה שנייה כביאה ראשונה *amru me'atah re'uyim hayu Yisrael la'asot
lahem nes bivi'ah sheniyah kivi'ah rishonah*, a miracle should have been done
when
they entered in
the
same type of miracles when
they
entered in
the time of עזרא *Ezra* like
when
they entered
in
the time of יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*. אלא Ela, שגרם החטא *ela shegaram
hachet*, but the sin caused that it was not with miracles. רש״י
*Rashi* makes an important point. It was not just the absence of
miracles, it was the question of whether you're going in as a
sovereign nation or whether you're going
in under the authority of מלך בבל *Melech Bavel* and only with
their permission and you're settling the land rather than conquering the land.
Okay, so there was a significant difference there. It wasn't just the
presence of miracles. רש״י *Rashi* says משתעבדים למלכות *mishta'abadim lemalchut*, the question
was whether they subject to a foreign kingdom. Okay. ואחר כך הביאו
את האבנים *ve'achar kach hevi'u et ha'avanim*. So now, on the same
day they flew all the way to גריזים Gerizim והר עיבל v'Har
Eival. *Gerizim veHar Eval*, okay? And then they brought the same stones
again. Not clear in דברים Devarim *Devarim* that they were, well, דברים
Devarim *Devarim* has the stones that were erected. But anyway, but certainly
not clear in יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua* at all that these were the,
because in יהושע Yehoshua, *Yehoshua* it was like many, many months apart.
But anyway, according to this, the
same stones that they erected in גלגל Gilgal. *Gilgal*, והביאו את האבנים
ובנו את המזבח *vehevi'u et ha'avanim uvanu et hamizbe'ach*. And they built
the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*. Now it's sounding like, and here's another way
of dealing with
the ambiguity
in
the פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim*, what was the תורה
Torah, *Torah* written on? That actually has that it seems like the
stones were used, it's not clear. When it says והביאו את האבנים
ובנו את המזבח *vehevi'u et ha'avanim uvanu et hamizbe'ach*, but the implication
is that
those stones that had been erected in
גלגל *Gilgal* were now used to build a מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*. And
then, okay, we'll get to that. וסדו בסיד וכתבו עליהם את כל
דברי התורה בשבעים לשון *vesadu vasid vechatvu aleihem et kol divrei hatorah
beshivim lashon*. So there you satisfy all the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*, yeah?
You have to appreciate what this is doing, right? It satisfies the
ambiguity in דברים *Devarim* of was it written on the stones or
was it written on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. It also satisfies the
point that in
the תורה Torah *Torah* it has the תורה Torah *Torah* speaks, again,
maybe I didn't make this clear,
the תורה Torah *Torah* speaks about both
those things happening at הר גריזים והר עיבל Har Gerizim v'Har Eival.
*Har Gerizim veHar Eval*:
the erecting of the stones and the building of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*.
In יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*, the erecting of
the stones
happened at גלגל *Gilgal* and the building of the מזבח *mizbe'ach* happened
at הר גריזים והר עיבל Har Gerizim v'Har Eival? *Har Gerizim veHar
Eval*. So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s done is it solved the
problem. It brought it all together. It used the same stones, so
we have both the erecting of
the stones
and the מזבח *mizbe'ach* happening sort of at the same, at the
same time and sort of in the
same place or
the stones get erected twice and they become part of the מזבח
*mizbe'ach* so we solved the ambiguity of where it was written on.
Maybe somebody would say they transported the stones. והביאו את האבנים *vehevi'u
et ha'avanim*. Okay. ובנו מזבח *uvanu mizbe'ach*. And this is the end
of the discussion before where it says they erected the stones. It's
clear, so it's pulling all the things together to resolve the problems
and the ambiguities.
וכתבו את כל דברי התורה בשבעים לשון *vechatvu et kol divrei hatorah
beshivim lashon*, שנאמר shenemar, באר היטב *she'ne'emar be'er heitev*. והעלו עולות ושלמים
ואכלו ושתו ושמחו וברכו וקיללו *vehe'elu olot ushlamim ve'achlu vashatu vesamchu berchu
vekillalu*. That's a funny phrase, right? They ate, they drank, they rejoiced,
they blessed and they cursed. It's sounding like ברכו *berchu* is like
it sounds like they blessed God. No, but anyway, they did the
ברכות brachot *berchot* and the קללות klalot. *klalot*. וקיפלו את האבנים *vekiplu
et ha'avanim*. And then they folded up. Now does that mean לקפל
*lekapel*, does that mean they removed the plaster? It a little bit
evokes that, but it doesn't sound like that. It sounds like they,
because now you've got a problem, because where were the אבנים *avanim*,
where did the stones remain erected? According to יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*, they
were erected in גלגל *Gilgal*. But here they've been taken from the
ירדן Yarden *Yarden*, brought all the way to הר גריזים Har Gerizim
והר עיבל Eival *Har Gerizim veHar Eval*. When are they going to
get erected in גלגל *Gilgal*? So that's going to be after that.
They backtrack. ובאו ולנו בגלגל *uvau valanu beGilgal*, שנאמר והעברתם אותם עמכם
והנחתם אותם במלון *she'ne'emar ve'ha'avartem otam imachem vehinachtem otam bamalon*. יכול בכל
מלון ומלון *yachol bechol malon umalon*? Maybe you put it in any
place that you happen to sleep? תלמוד לומר אשר תלינו בו הלילה
*talmud lomar asher talinu bo halailah*, where you're going to sleep there
tonight. וכתיב ואת שתים עשרה האבנים האלה אשר לקחו *vechtiv ve'et shteim
esreh ha'avanim ha'eleh asher lakechu*, that they took from the ירדן Yarden,
*Yarden*
they erected in
the גלגל *Gilgal*. So basically you read the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*, it
says
the stones that they took
they erected in גלגל *Gilgal*. And what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does
is it says wait, wait, wait. Before that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* happened
after they left the ירדן Yarden, *Yarden*,
the stones they took, we have to jump forward
from פרק ד *Perek Dalet* to פרק ח *Perek Chet*. We have
to read the whole story of הר גריזים Har Gerizim והר עיבל
*Har Gerizim veHar Eval*, okay? That happened on the same day, okay?
And they used those
stones
at הר גריזים Har Gerizim והר עיבל *Har Gerizim veHar Eval* to
build
the מזבח *mizbe'ach*
to write the תורה Torah, *Torah*, etc., there. Then let's get back
to פרק ד *Perek Dalet*. Oh, by the way, those stones now
they brought back to גלגל *Gilgal* and they erected in גלגל *Gilgal*.
Right, exactly, exactly. Exactly, they didn't stop at גלגל, they didn't—the first
thing they did with the stones when they took them out of
the ירדן Yarden is they brought them to הר גריזים Har Gerizim
and הר עיבל, Har Eival, did the מזבח, did the writing of
the תורה, Torah. brought them back to גלגל. Right, exactly. Okay. Anyway,
the point is that you have to appreciate that it is taking
an ambiguity
in דברים
about what the תורה was written on, the stones that were
erected or the
stones of the מזבח, and saying
the answer is yes, they were the same stones. And b, what
it's doing is it's taking
what the תורה has as one event, the erecting
of
the stones and the מזבח, and יהושע Yehoshua has these two events
separated a great deal: erecting of
the stones
right after the ירדן, the מזבח in גריזים and עיבל much, much
later, and bringing them together again. So the גמרא Gemara is sort
of solving
the problems
in the פסוקים, which you weren't aware of, which I wasn't aware
of until I read the פסוקים again last night. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תנא צירעה לא עברה עמהן. Tana,
tzira lo avra imahen. Now the צירעה, tzira, the wasps, the ברייתא
baraita says ושלחתי את הצירעה לפניכם... v'shalachti et hatzira lifneichem... anyway, ושלחתי
את הצירעה לפניכם, v'shalachti et hatzira lifneichem, is that the פסוק? pasuk
Anyway, I will send these wasps before you and they'll help drive
out the nation. So the ברייתא baraita says it didn't go with
them. I don't know where the ברייתא baraita is getting that, maybe
because it's not
in the story in יהושע. So something happened, it didn't go.
The גמרא Gemara says ולא והא כתיב ושלחתי את הצירעה לפניך? v'lo?
v'ha ksiv v'shalachti et hatzira lifanecha? I will send it before you.
So you could have said like גרם החטא garam hachet or something,
but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש על שפת ירדן עמדה. Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish, al sfat
Yarden amda. No, no, no, the צירעה tzira was sent before them
but didn't actually cross into the border. Maybe the problem that the
ברייתא baraita is dealing with is who needs a lot of צירעה
tzira in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, who needs all those wasps? So
they stood right at the edge, like hovered maybe over the ירדן,
okay, עמדה וזרקה בהן מרה. amda v'zarka bahen mara. And it sort
of, what is it, a snake? There's like the spitting cobra. You
know about the spitting cobra? Like sort of these were the spitting
צירעה. tzira. They spat out their venom across, you know, without actually
crossing the border of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It was the first
chemical warfare I guess. Okay, anyway, וסמתה עיניהם. v'simta eineihem. It blinded
the eyes of the enemy. I mean the enemy would have to
very conveniently line up by the ירדן in
order to get hit. So anyway, okay, so the venom flew. It
was a guided missile. וסמתה עיניהם מלמעלה, v'simsa eineihem milmala, it blinded
their eyes above, וסרסתן מלמטה, v'sersatan milmata, and it castrated them below.
שנאמר ואנכי השמדתי את האמורי מפניהם, She'ne'emar v'anochi hishmarti et haEmori mipneichem,
I destroyed the Amorite before you, before them, אשר כגובה ארזים גובהו,
asher k'govah arazim gavho, that its height is like that of the
cedar trees, וחסון הוא כאלון, v'chason hu ka'alon, and it's as mighty
as the—what's an אלון? alon? An oak. ואשמיד פריו ממעל, Va'ashmid piryo
mimal, I destroyed the fruit from above, ושרשיו מתחת, v'sharashav mitachat, and
the roots below. So the roots also is what gives maybe life,
future life also. So anyway, so they were wiped out the eyes
and they were castrated. Okay. רב פפא אמר שתי צירעות הוו. Rav
Papa amar, shtei tzirot havai. No, no, no, there were two צירעות.
tzirot. חדא דמשה, Chada d'Moshe, the one of Moshe, וחדא דיהושע. v'chada
d'Yehoshua. דמשה לא עבר, D'Moshe lo avar, of Moshe did not cross
over, דיהושע עבר. d'Yehoshua avar. But there was a צירעה tzira that
went in with יהושע and that fulfilled the פסוק pasuk of ושלחתי
את הצירעה. v'shalachti et hatzira. I really don't know, I didn't have
a chance to check the מהרש"א Maharsha or anyone else, but like
there's no פסוק pasuk that it's trying to solve. If it has
it going over with יהושע, it's not that it's offended by the
idea that there's צירעה tzira in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So why say there are two? What's the
problem of saying that the צירעה tzira of Moshe went with him?
Unless maybe again, the problem is that maybe the assumption would be
if it was that powerful, if we associate it with Moshe we're
going to associate it with tremendously powerful, it doesn't explain the challenges
they had in their battles. The battles were not so easy, you
know? So maybe it's somehow trying to deal with that. And Moshe's
צירעה tzira did spit its venom? No, according to this he presumably,
the second version presumably holds that Moshe's צירעה tzira didn't do anything.
It was a different צירעה tzira of יהושע. It didn't have, I
don't know. Maybe it did spit the venom but it wasn't, I
don't know. Anyway, I don't know the answer. Okay. Yeah. Because it
didn't cross over to ארץ... Eretz... It didn't cross over. Right. Okay,
I don't know. I did not get a chance to look at
the מהרש"א. Maharsha. All right, that was a good one Rabbi Dov.
Good. All right. לו לא באתי אלא לכך, Luvei lo bati ela
l'chach, for that it was דיינו. dayeinu. Okay, fine. Let me just
take a quick glance. I don't want to skip the מהרש"א Maharsha
just very quickly to see if he says anything. Okay, so the
מהרש"א Maharsha says that part of the problem is that the פסוק
pasuk that says את הצירעה et hatzira only mentions the כנעני Kna'ani
and the חתי, Chiti, and it does not mention the other אומות.
umot. So he thinks that the גמרא Gemara is trying to solve
the problem that you know... Anyways, so I'll take a look at
it later and tell you if I see anything else. But there's
certainly some problem that it's trying to solve. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara, goes on. ששה שבטים עלו לראש הר גריזים. Shisha shevatim
alu lerosh Har Gerizim. Now we finally get, all of that was
describing the whole narrative, now we finally get to the actual events
of the ברכות brachot and the קללות. klalot. Six of the tribes
on הר גריזים Har Gerizim and six on הר עיבל. Har Eival.
So מה החציו? mah hatziyav? Now there's a פסוק pasuk? in יהושע
that I was reading to you before says the following. Here's the
one פסוק Pasuk? that speaks about the actual acts of the ברכות
brachot and the קללות. klalot, וכל ישראל וזקניו ושוטריו ושופטיו עומדים מזה
ומזה לארון נגד הכהנים הלוים נשאי ארון ברית ה' כגר כאזרח חציו
אל מול הר גריזים והחציו אל מול הר עיבל כאשר צוה משה
עבד ה' לברך את עם ישראל בראשנה. Vechol Yisrael u'zekanav veshotrav veshofetav
omdim mizeh umizeh la'aron neged hakohanim halevi'im nosei aron berit Hashem, kager
ka'ezrach, chetzyo el mul Har Gerizim vehachetzyo el mul Har Eival, ka'asher
tzivah Moshe eved Hashem levarech et am Yisrael barishonah. So it says
והחציו, vehachetzyo, half here and the half on the other. Now by
the way in terms of הר גריזים Har Gerizim. and הר עיבל,
Har Eival, until today הר גריזים Har Gerizim which is where the
ברכות brachot were is lush and you know very green and you
know vegetation growing and הר עיבל Har Eival is completely desolate. So
obviously symbolically, I'm not saying that was the effect of the ברכות
brachot and the קללות, klalot. symbolically that that's the one is for
the ברכות and the other's for the קללות. It's a very powerful...
the question I do wonder about is the fact in יהושע it
says אל מול הר גריזים el mul Har Gerizim and אל מול
הר עיבל el mul Har Eival and the פסוקים in דברים say,
you know, that they shall stand על הר גריזים. al Har Gerizim.
So the difference is are you standing between them and like, you
know, alongside them or are you actually going up onto the mountains?
But anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is focusing on והחציו. vehachetzyo.
What's the והחציו? vehachetzyo? אמר רב כהנא כדרך שחלוקים כאן כך חלוקים
באבני אפוד. Amar Rav Kahana: Kederech shechalukim kan, kach chalukim be'avnei efod.
It's to refer to the fact that these these are two halves
that are recognized elsewhere. The same way they're divided on the mountains,
they're divided on the stones of the אבני אפוד. avnei efod. Okay,
מיתיבי Meitivei says the גמרא, Gemara asks about that. שתי אבנים טובות
היו לו לכהן גדול על כתפיו אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן ושמות שנים
עשר שבטים כתוב עליהם ששה על אבן זו וששה על אבן זו
שנאמר ששה משמותם על האבן האחת ואת שמות הששה הנותרים על האבן
השנית כתולדותם. Shtei avanim tovot hayu lo lekohen gadol al ketfav, achat
mikan ve'achat mikan, ushemot shenei asar shevatim katuv aleihem. Shishah al even
zo veshishah al even zo, shene'emar shishah mishemotam al ha'even ha'achat ve'et
shemot hashishah hano'tarim al ha'even hashenit ketoldotam. And now it says a
דרשה. drashah. It says שנית כתולדותם ולא ראשונה כתולדותם. Shenit ketoldotam velo
rishonah ketoldotam. The second one was the order of birth not the
first one. Why? מפני Mipnei because the whole things were essentially the
birth order, but in the first six you have ראובן שמעון לוי
יהודה, Reuven, Shimon, Levi, Yehudah, right? So ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה, Reuven,
Shimon, Levi, Yehudah, but the problem is that יהודה Yehudah has to
come first because he's the leader. So מפני שיהודה מוקדם. Mipnei she'Yehudah
mukdam. So that was the only one that was out of order.
Okay. וחמשים אותיות היו. Vachamishim otiyot hayu. And there were 25 letters
on each stone. עשרים וחמש על אבן זו ועשרים וחמש על אבן
זו. Esrim vechamishah al even zo ve'esrim vechamishah al even zo. So
if you count the
letters
in
the name, it's actually a perfect division. Except as the גמרא's Gemara
going to point out it's not a perfect... it's 24 and 25,
but pretty close. The גמרא Gemara will solve that problem
in a minute. Okay. Okay, so so yeah, right, well that's one
answer. Okay. So anyway, that's the division. Okay, so the first are
יהודה ראובן שמעון, Yehudah, Reuven, Shimon, I mean ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה
Reuven, Shimon, Levi, Yehudah but יהודה Yehudah goes first, and then I
know I know and then דן ונפתלי, Dan ve'Naftali, right? Because דן
ונפתלי Dan ve'Naftali were then born afterwards, okay, and the others are
then
it continues
in the birth order. So that's the first division. רבי חנינא בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel omer, רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi
Chanina ben Gamliel disagrees and he says לא כדרך שחלוקים בחומש הפקודים.
Lo kederech shechalukim bechumash hapikudim. Not like the way they're
divided in במדבר, Bamidbar, which is basically more or less the birth
order, which is the
first opinion. Okay, אלא כדרך שחלוקים בחומש שני. Ella kederech shechalukim bechumash
sheni. Interesting phrase, חומש שני. chumash sheni. Anyway, but anyway
in שמות, Shemot, I know, but interesting what phrase חומש הפקודים, chumash
hapikudim, חומש שני, chumash sheni, חומש הגאולה, chumash hageulah, I don't know
what you want to call it, you know anyway. Okay, but anyway,
but what is that? It's the opening of שמות. Shemot. ואלה שמות
בני ישראל ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה יששכר זבולון ובנימין. Ve'eleh shemot benei
Yisrael: Reuven, Shimon, Levi, Yehudah, Yissachar, Zevulun, u'Vinyamin. Now יששכר זבולון Yissachar
Zevulun is not the birth order, דן ונפתלי Dan ve'Naftali come next
in the birth order. What יששכר זבולון Yissachar Zevulun is that accounting
is: ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה יששכר זבולון Reuven, Shimon, Levi, Yehudah, Yissachar,
Zevulun is all is לאה's Leah children, is all of לאה's Leah
children, right? ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה Reuven, Shimon, Levi, Yehudah and then
יששכר וזבולון. Yissachar ve'Zevulun. And then the next and then the remainder
is רחל Rachel and the and בלהה Bilhah and זלפה's Zilpah children.
כיצד: Keitzad: so how does that work out? בני לאה כסדרן, Benei
Leah kesidran, so בני לאה
benei Leah
are listed
in their birth order but they're all listed together, that's the way
they are in the beginning of שמות. Shemot. ובני רחל, Uvenei Rachel,
אחד מכאן ואחד מכאן, echad mikan ve'echad mikan, it starts with because
the way שמות Shemot starts is... שמעון לוי יהודה יששכר זבולון ובנימין.
Shimon, Levi, Yehuda, Yissochor, Zevulun, u-Vinyamin. So בנימין Vinyamin is the first,
completely out of order, right? בנימין דן ונפתלי גד ואשר Vinyamin, Dan
v'Naftali, Gad v'Asher and then יוסף. Yosef. So you have one of
בני רחל's b'nei Rachel first, בנימין,
Vinyamin,
the שפחות
shfachos
in the middle, and then ending with יוסף. Yosef. Okay? בני רחל
b'nei Rachel אחד מכאן ואחד מכאן echad mikan v'echad mikan ובני שפחות
u-v'nei shfachos באמצע. b'emtza. What do we mean by מכאן? mikan? Meaning
just the top and the bottom of this no, no, of the
second stone. ואלא מה אני מקיים כתולדתם? v'ela mah ani mekayem k'toldosam?
But the פסוק says that they're put on the stones
כתולדתם. k'toldosam. Okay? נו, nu, well the first one is right. So
you could say the first one is כתולדתם k'toldosam within the grouping
of one woman's children. But anyway, but it sounds like they're all
כתולדתם. k'toldosam. And it says השני כתולדתם hasheini k'toldosam על אבן השני
דוקא, al even hasheini davka, and the second one is not at
all כתולדתם. k'toldosam. So the גמרא Gemara says כשמות שקרא להם אביהן.
kishmos shekara lahem avihen. It doesn't mean the birth's order, it means
the names that they were given by their father, ולא כשמות שקרא
להם משה, v'lo kishmos shekara lahem Moshe, not a later name associated
like משה. What does that mean? So ראובן Reuven ולא ראובני, v'lo
Reuveni, שמעון Shimon ולא שמעוני, v'lo Shimoni, דן Dan ולא הדני, v'lo
hadani, גד Gad ולא הגדי. v'lo hagadi. Now that seems a little
trivial because משה isn't really changing their names, he's just identifying the
tribe. But I think that's exactly his point. How do we understand
the names that were on the אבני אפוד? avnei efod? Did they
represent the tribes, or did they represent the twelve sons? Right? Is
it שמות בני ישראל? shmos b'nei Yisrael? Like who's ישראל Yisrael, in
that פסוק? Is ישראל the Israel people, right, and it's essentially the
names of the twelve tribes? Or is ישראל, no, יעקב's Yaakov children?
So what he is saying is, and that's completely consistent, don't give
me a birth order in במדבר, Bamidbar, don't give me an order
that the tribes are listed
in במדבר, Bamidbar, that's an order of the tribes. I don't care
about the order of the tribes, I care about the order of
the children. So when are the children listed? In the beginning of
שמות. Shemos. So that actually works very beautifully. He says we're going
to go to שמות Shemos and have them as children, as sons,
you know, as people, not as tribes, and that's what כתולדתם k'toldosam
means. I don't want their tribe names, I want their personal names.
אה, ah, כתולדתם k'toldosam doesn't mean an order? No, it means by
the names that they were given in their birth. It refers to
their birth, it refers to them as real people, right? So I
don't know, I think there's something very powerful. On the one hand
you could say it's not as representative if it doesn't refer to
a tribe, but on the other hand there's something very personal about
carrying the names of those twelve people in, you know, it's, you
know, as opposed to the abstraction of the names of the twelve
tribes. So I think there's a really very sort of deep debate
here between these two approaches. Anyway, the point is either of those
approaches is not the order, is not the division of הר גריזים
Har Gerizim והר עיבל. He says, ולא. v'lo. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיובתא דרב כהנא תיובתא. tiyuvta d'Rav Kahana tiyuvta. You're right, because
those two approaches, neither of them are the order of הר גריזים
Har Gerizim והר עיבל. What's the order of הר גריזים Har Gerizim.
והר עיבל? So, of course, I'm sure you all know it by
heart, but if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he'll says,
I'm kidding. תיובתא דרב כהנא, tiyuvta d'Rav Kahana, third line down in
the narrow lines, רש"י Rashi says לכולי עלמא אין זה סדר הר
גריזים והר עיבל. l'kulei alma ein zeh seder Har Gerizim v'Har Eival.
ואילו סדר הר גריזים שמעון ולוי ויהודה ויששכר ויוסף ובנימין. v'ilu seder
Har Gerizim Shimon v'Levi v'Yehuda v'Yissochor v'Yosef u-Vinyamin. Okay? So that's basically
who is that? It's not ראובן, Reuven, it's שמעון לוי יהודה יששכר,
Shimon, Levi, Yehuda, Yissochor, now not, not זבולון, Zevulun, and so we
have like four of לאה's Leah children but not two of them.
And then, and then יוסף ובנימין. Yosef u-Vinyamin. והר עיבל ראובן גד
ואשר זבולון דן ונפתלי. v'Har Eival Reuven Gad v'Asher Zevulun Dan v'Naftali.
So anyway, so okay, so Michael reasonably says okay, so that seems
an arbitrary order, I'll get back to that in a minute. But
either way, it is not the division on the stones, okay, which
is a more logical division. It does not reflect the division of
the stones. So the גמרא Gemara says ואלא מאי והחציה? v'ela mai
v'hachatziyah? So back to the question, what does והחציה v'hachatziyah mean if
it doesn't represent the division on the stones? So תנא חציה של
מול הר גריזים מרובה מחציה של הר עיבל. tana hatziyah shel mool
Har Gerizim merubah michatziyah shel Har Eival. והחציה v'hachatziyah על הר עיבל
al Har Eival now somehow means that it was, I don't know,
well I'll
tell you in a minute what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says,
but somehow it means that the half on הר עיבל Har Eival
was not the same size, but of course it somehow was a
smaller half. Okay, it was half of the tribes,
but smaller in
number. Okay, so maybe והחציה v'hachatziyah is read and the other half,
the other half because the real half, the big half, right, is
it's like, you know, I, you know, I want the bigger half.
There's no such thing as a bigger half. Well here there's a
bigger half, okay, because it's half the tribes but bigger in
number. So the one half was there and the other half, the
smaller half, was on הר עיבל. Har Eival. Okay, חציה שמול הר
גריזים מרובה מחציה שעל הר עיבל. hatziyah shemool Har Gerizim merubah michatziyah
she'al Har Eival. מפני שלוי למטה. mipnei she-Levi lemata. Now לוי Levi
was below. Now that's funny. לוי Levi was on הר גריזים. Har
Gerizim So הר גריזים Har Gerizim, is more, why is מפני שלוי
למטה? mipnei she-Levi lemata? אדרבה מפני שלוי למטה בציר להו. adaraba mipnei
she-Levi lemata batzir lehu. That makes הר גריזים Har Gerizim, less. So
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, אף על פי שלוי למטה, af al pi
she-Levi lemata, although some of לוי Levi was below, not all of
לוי, Levi, but a lot of the כהנים והלוים kohanim v'ha-Levi'im were
below. Okay, because although some of לוי Levi was below, nevertheless there
הר גריזים Har Gerizim was still bigger
in number, בדי יוסף עמהם, bidei Yosef imahem, because בני יוסף b'nei
Yosef was on הר גריזים. Har Gerizim That makes made up for
the difference and they were still a much larger population than הר
עיבל. Har Eival. How do we know יוסף Yosef was so large?
שנאמר, וידברו בני יוסף את יהושע לאמר מדוע נתתה לי נחלה, Vayidabru
Bnei Yosef et Yehoshua lemor madua natatah li nachalah, גורל אחד, goral
echad, why did you only give me one portion of the land,
וחבל אחד, ve-chevel echad, ואני עם רב, ve-ani am rav, I'm a
very large people, we can't deal with only one portion. ויאמר אליהם
יהושע, Vayomer aleihem Yehoshua, אם עם רב אתה, im am rav ata,
if you're such a populous nation, so עלה לך היערה, aleh lecha
ha-ya'arah, go to the forest and conquer more land. So the גמרא
Gemara is- it's a funny sort of way, go to the forest.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר להם לכו והחביאו עצמכם ביערים, amar
lahem lechu ve-hachvi'u atzmechem be-ye'arim, hide yourself- oh, that- you're so large?
Here's some good advice. Keep yourselves hidden in the forest. Why? שלא
תשלוט בכם עין הרע. she-lo tishlot bachem ayin hara. You don't want
the עין הרע, ayin hara, you're so large, you know, people say
oh, you know, that'll lead to an עין הרע. ayin hara. So
you gotta not- don't like, you know, don't announce that, you know,
keep it quiet, go
hide yourselves in the forest. אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to
him, no,
we don't need that advice.
זרעיה דיוסף לא שלטה ביה עינא בישא.
zar'eih de-Yosef
lo shaltah beih eina bisha.
The seed of יוסף, Yosef, the
עין הרע ayin hara has no power over. שנתכתב, she-nitchatev, because the
verse says, בן פורת יוסף, Ben porat Yosef, a- like a- flowering,
flourishing son is יוסף, Yosef, בן פורת עלי עין, Ben porat alei
ayin, a flourishing son over the wellspring. ואמר רבי אבהו, ve-amar Rabi
Abbahu, אל תקרי עלי עין, al tikrei alei ayin, over by the
wellspring, אלא עולי עין, ela olei ayin, they rise above the evil
eye. רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר מהכא, Rabi Yosei bar Chanina amar
mehacha, וידגו לרוב בקרב הארץ, ve-yidgu la-rov be-kerev ha-aretz, this is the
ברכה bracha that יעקב Yaakov gave to the children of יוסף, Yosef,
they shall flourish like- for- many in the land. מה דגים שבים,
ma dagim she-ba-yam, the word וידגו ve-yidgu is like the fish, what
is the way with the fish of the sea, מים מכסים עליהם,
mayim mechassim aleihem, the water covers them, ואין עין שולטת בהם, ve-ein
ayin sholetet bahem, so the eye doesn't have- can't see them, doesn't
have power over them, the evil eye, אף זרעו של יוסף, af
zar'o shel Yosef, אין עין שולטת בהם. ein ayin sholetet bahem. Okay,
now. So basically, but bottom line is is that the הר גריזים
Har Gerizim was more numerous. Now, if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, to look back at תוספות Tosafot of ל"ו עמוד א',
lamed vav amud aleph, מהי והחציו, mahi ve-hachetzyo, תוספות Tosafot says, לשון
ירושלמי, lashon Yerushalmi, ישוב יוסף, Yishuv Yosef, the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi's version is
better. דגרסינן התם, de-garsinan hatam, מה תלמוד לומר והחציו, ma talmud lomar
ve-hachetzyo, מלמד שמועטים בהר גריזים ומרובים בהר עיבל. melamed she-mu'atim be-Har Gerizim
u-merubim be-Har Eival. The half on הר עיבל Har Eival sounds like
not so small a half, sounds like the bigger half. Okay, בהר
עיבל. be-Har Eival. למה? lamah? שאין שבטו של לוי כולו שם. she-ein
shivto shel Levi kulo sham. And now it fits the end of
that ברייתא, braita, because לוי Levi wasn't up, the full tribe of
לוי Levi wasn't on הר גריזים, Har Gerizim so the הר עיבל
Har Eival side was larger. Okay. תוספות, Tosafot, מהי והחציו, mahi ve-hachetzyo,
ל"ו עמוד א'. lamed vav amud aleph. שאם היה כל שבט לוי
שם היו שווים. she-im hayah kol shevet Levi sham hayu shavim. Because
had they been there, they would be equal. רבי שמואל בר נחמני
בשם רבי יונתן אמר, Rabi Shmuel bar Nachmani be-shem Rabi Yonatan amar,
אפילו היה כל שבטו של לוי שם לא היו שווים. afilu hayah
kol shivto shel Levi sham lo hayu shavim. Okay, למה, lamah, even
if לוי Levi was full of לוי Levi was up on הר
גריזים, Har Gerizim הר גריזים Har Gerizim would still be smaller. First
wide line of תוספות. Tosafot. למה, lamah, why? שכבר נפלו משבטו של
שמעון עשרים וארבעה אלף איש, she-kevar naflu mi-shivto shel Shimon esrim ve-arba'ah
elef ish, right, שמעון Shimon had been decimated by the whole thing
with- with פנחס, Pinchas, right? So- and- so therefore the numbers on
הר גריזים were going to be less regardless. Okay. And then it
goes a little bit about this, and now if you take a
look at תוספות Tosafot says like this. ומיהו, u-mihu, three lines down
in the middle of the line, three lines in the wide lines,
תוספות Tosafot says, כשתדקדק במנין אחרון שנאמר בו, ke-she-tedakdek be-minyan acharon she-nemar
bo, אלה הפקודים, eleh ha-pekudim, and now תוספות Tosafot does the math.
One minute. We actually have some numbers. Let's go look at the
end of במדבר, Bamidbar, where it does the numbers, and that's right
before they enter into the land, and let's actually tabulate how many
people are on הר גריזים and how many people are on הר
עיבל. Har Eival. What a thought. So תוספות Tosafot says, if you
actually tabulate it, okay, לאחר שמתו מתי מדבר, le-achar she-metu metei midbar,
כדכתיב באלה הפקודים, ki-de-chtiv be-eleh ha-pekudim, ויהי בשנת הארבעים לאחר פטירת אהרן,
vayehi bi-shnat ha-arba'im le-achar ptirat Aharon, דכתיב ויעל אהרן וימת שם בשנת
הארבעים, di-chtiv vaya'al Aharon vayamot sham bi-shnat ha-arba'im, והכי מוכח בסדר עולם.
ve-hachi mukhach be-Seder Olam. תמצא, timtza, now five lines down towards the
end of the line, תמצא, timtza, so if you do the math,
you do the computation- I shouldn't say math, I once had a
math professor in my- in my דף יומי Daf Yomi class or
my גמרא Gemara class, and I said that once about some- I
said so if you do the math, he said, that's not math,
that's accounting. Anyway. So if you do the computation, if you do
the addition, תמצא במנין שבטים שעמדו על הר גריזים עודף על אותם
שעמדו על הר עיבל תשעת אלפים חסר ק"ל. timtza be-minyan shvatim she-amdu
al Har Gerizim odef al otam she-amdu al Har Eival tish'at alafim
chasar kuf lamed. So תוספות Tosafot says, actually, if you do the
math, it's pretty darn close. הר גריזים is 9,000 more, so that's
consistent with our גמרא Gemara that הר גריזים was more. But if
you take out לוי, Levi, there was 8,000 לוי. Levi. Okay, so
if you take and the לוי Levi was on the bottom. So
actually, it was almost exactly the same, once you remove לוי, Levi,
it was only a difference of 1,000. And that's more consistent with
our גמרא Gemara that says הר גריזים was more. So I can
point you, I remember reading now 20 years ago or something, somebody
wrote this whole article on this issue about what was the division
of the שבטים, shvatim, did all the different tabulations, you know, about
this. I think the basic point was to say like this was
the way the תורה divided it was the only possible of getting
it as close as possible to an equal division or something. Anyway.
I think that that's what the article says. I think it just
works out all the permutations. I don't remember. There was more to
it than that. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. We
are now back on ל"ו עמוד ב', Lamed Vav Amud Bet, five
lines down in the middle section. הני חמישים אותיות, Hani Hamishim Otiyot,
גמרא Gemara says if we assume that it's listed in their birth
order and you count up the letters, it said that it was
equal, half and half. It's not equal. חמישים וכי חדה הווי? Hamishim
Vechi Chada Havei? It's 49, not 50, and it's also not equal;
25 and 24. אמר רבי יצחק יוסף הוסיפו לו אות אחת, Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak, Yosef Hosifu Lo Ot Achat, שנאמר עדות ביהוסף שמו בצאתו
על ארץ מצרים. Shene'emar Edut Bihosef Samo Betzeito Al Eretz Mitzrayim. So
there's one place where יוסף Yosef is referred to with an extra
ה, Heh, יהוסף. Yehosef. So therefore that was he was written with
the extra ה Heh and that made it 25 and 25 and
made it 50. מתיב ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק, Metiv Lei Rav
Nachman Bar Yitzchak, כתולדותם בעינן. Ketoldotam Ba'inan. You need כתולדותם, Ketoldotam, which
we've been saying according to this approach means birth order, but we're
going to assume here that it also means consistent with the names
and that was not a name that he had in when he
was in his life. אלא, here's the answer. כל התורה כולה בנימין
כתיב Kol HaTorah Kula Binyamin Ketiv without the י, Yud, והכא Vehacha
when he was born, בנימין שלם כתיב, Binyamin Shalem Ketiv, it's written
with the י. Yud. דכתיב ואביו קרא לו בנימין. Dechtiv Va'aviv Kara
Lo Binyamin. So he was actually דוקא Davka it works out very
well. It is כתולדותם Ketoldotam the way it's spelled when he was
born, and that makes it 25 and 25 and that makes it
50. It's actually interesting, when there's some people have a מנהג, Minhag,
not that it's parallel not about בנימין, Binyamin, but about with the
first time they read the word יששכר Issachar in
the תורה, they read it יששכר. Yissaschar. Spelled the exact way, but
it's sort of יש שכר Yesh Sachar whatever, so to actually bring
out this particular spelling of the name. אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא
אמר רבי שמעון חסידא, Amar Rav Chana Bar Bizna Amar Rabbi Shimon
Chasida, יוסף, Yosef, now that we're talking about יוסף, Yosef, יוסף שקידש
שם שמיים בסתר, Yosef Shekidesh Shem Shamayim Beseter, יוסף Yosef that sanctified
God's name in
private, הוסיפו לו אות אחת משמו. Hosifu Lo Ot Achat Mishmo. He
got the ה, Heh, יהוסף, Yehosef, one of God's letters. משמו של
הקדוש ברוך הוא. Mishmo Shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. יהודה שקידש שם שמיים
בפרהסיא, Yehuda Shekidesh Shem Shamayim Befarhesia, יהודה Yehuda who publicly sanctified God's
name, נקרא כולו על שמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. Nikra Kulo Al
Shemo Shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. So יהודה Yehuda has all the letters
of God's name with an extra דלת. Dalet. It has a י
Yud and a ה Heh and a ו Vav and a ה,
Heh, so his whole name reflects God's name. Now just to tell
you because we're not going to get to יהודה Yehuda till tomorrow,
but of course I think naturally we'd be inclined to think that
this week's פרשה, Parsha, he did it in
public, he announced to everybody, it was a whole court case, everybody's
there and he accepted responsibility. Interestingly though the גמרא is going to
talk about not actually the person of יהודה Yehuda but the tribe
of יהודה Yehuda and the story of נחשון בן עמינדב Nachshon Ben
Aminadav jumping into the ים סוף, Yam Suf, which is very funny
because it's all very personal about יהודה Yehuda and יוסף, Yosef, קידש
שם שמיים Kidesh Shem Shamayim and this is the most obvious thing
is to associate this with the story in this week's פרשה. Parsha.
Anyway, now we're going to focus on יוסף. Yosef. So, now יוסף
מאי היא? Yosef Mai Hi? What's the story of יוסף? Yosef? I
mean we know the story but let's spell it out. דכתיב, Dechtiv,
the verse says, דכתיב Dechtiv it says ויהי כיום הזה ויבוא הביתה
לעשות מלאכתו. Vayehi Kayom Hazeh Vayavo Habayta La'asot Melachto. It was a
particular day, he came to the home to the house to do
his work. אמר רבי יוחנן מלמד ששניהם לדבר עבירה נתכוונו. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Melamed Sheshneihem Lidvar Aveira Nitkavnu. They both were intending to sin.
מלאכתו Melachto means he was finally going to take care of his
desire or give in to his business, exactly. So thank you. תוספות
Tosafot says what's pushing him to say that? Meaning why would we
say such a thing that's not complimentary to יוסף? Yosef? What's
the
hint
in the פסוק? So he says it's the juxtaposition of ויבוא Vayavo
and לעשות מלאכתו La'asot Melachto and ויבוא Vayavo has an association with
ביאה and sex. That's how תוספות Tosafot understands it. ויבוא הביתה לעשות
מלאכתו. Vayavo Habayta La'asot Melachto. רב ושמואל, Rav Ushmuel, חד אמר, Chad
Amar, where were we? I'm sorry. Okay. מלמד ששניהם לדבר עבירה נתכוונו.
Melamed Sheshneihem Lidvar Aveira Nitkavnu. ויהי כיום הזה ויבוא הביתה לעשות מלאכתו,
Vayehi Kayom Hazeh Vayavo Habayta La'asot Melachto, so רב ושמואל, Rav Ushmuel,
חד אמר לעשות מלאכתו ממש. Chad Amar La'asot Melachto Mamash. So actually
there's a debate of רב ושמואל. Rav Ushmuel. One says it means
just to do his take care of his job. וחד אמר לעשות
צרכיו נכנס, Vechad Amar La'asot Tzorachav Nichnas, no his desires to do.
Okay so that's the debate. ואין איש מאנשי הבית שם בבית. Ve'ein
Ish Me'anshei Habayit Sham Babayit. Nobody of nobody in the household was
there. אפשר בית גדול כביתו של אותו רשע, Efshar Bayit Gadol Kevaito
Shel Oto Rasha, such a large house, the big household, so many
people and servants, לא היה בו איש? Lo Haya Bo Ish? How
could it be that it was completely empty? תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל,
Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael, אותו היום יום חגם היה. Oto Hayom Yom
Chagam Haya. It was their it was a day of a festival,
a holiday. והלכו כולם לבית עבודה זרה שלהם. Vehalchu Kulam Leveit Avoda
Zara Shelahem. And they all went to their house of worship, to
their pagan house of worship. והיא אמרה להן, Vehi Amra Lahen, and
she said to them, חולה היא היום, Chola Hi Hayom, I'm sick.
You guys go ahead. I'm not feeling well. אמרה, Amra, she said
to herself, she thought, אין לי יום שנזקק לי כיום הזה. Ein
Li Yom Shenizkak Li Kayom Hazeh. I will never have as good
as an opportunity as today. Everybody is leaving the house. So she
made an excuse to stay home. ותתפסהו בבגדו לאמר, Vatitpesehu Bevigdo Lemor,
and she grabbed him with his cloak to say sleep with me.
באותה שעה באה דמות דיוקנו של אביו. Be'ota Sha'a Ba'a Demut Dyukno
Shel Aviv. at that moment, the image of his father, דיוקנו diyukno
is the word for icon, okay, the image of his father appeared
to him. Now whether he was going intentionally to do that or
not, but at that moment, it was very, very hard to resist.
So the גמרא says he needed some help to resist. Okay, so
the image of his father appeared to him. ונראה לו בחלון Venireh
lo bachalon appeared to him in the window. אמר לו Amar lo
and he said to him, he actually spoke, it wasn't just the
image. יוסף, Yosef, עתידים אחיך שיכתבו על אבני אפוד, atidim achecha sheyichtevu
al avnei ephod, your brothers will be written on the אבני אפוד,
avnei ephod, so we're tying it back to the אבני אפוד. avnei
ephod. ואתה ביניהם, Ve'atah beneihem, you're going to be among them. רצונך
שימחה שמך מביניהם, Retzoncha sheyimacheh shimcha mibeneihem, do you want your name
to be wiped out? Again, not clear to me, I mean other
than the connection we had before. Oh, I didn't think about that.
Excellent. That is excellent, right? The being מוחה שם mocheh shem and
the presence by God in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, oh, that's
brilliant. שכוייח. Shkoiyach. Okay, that was even better than your sting operation.
That was real תורה. No, that was real good. Because I was
no because I was trying to understand other than the context that
we'd been talking about אבני אפוד, avnei ephod, why of all the
things to say how he's, you know, what he's jeopardizing, does it
mention jeopardizing his name on the אבני אפוד? avnei ephod? Like there's
a million other things you could say. Jeopardizing חלקו לעולם הבא, chelko
l'olam haba, jeopardizing being part of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. But I
think you're right, being מוחה השם mocheh hashem and here it's about
a man's sexual sin. That's really great, שכוייח. Shkoiyach. Okay. ותקרא רועה
זונות V'tikara ro'eh zonot and you'll be called a shepherd of prostitutes.
דכתיב רועה זונות יאבד הון Dechitiv ro'eh zonot ye'abed hon and the
one who shepherds prostitutes who you know flocks after the prostitutes will
waste great treasure. Throw away, you know, we know people throw away
a lot of their status and honor or whatever because they follow
their sexual desire. מיד, Miyad, so that did it for him. ותשב
באיתן קשתו Vatishav be'eitan kashto he put his strength in his literally
his bow. So bow is a very obviously phallic image, you know,
and the power of the need to release the tension. אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי מאיר ששב קשתו לאיתנו.
Amar Rabi Yochanan mishum Rabi Meir sheshav kashto
l'eitano. The רש"י Rashi says it reads the semen returned to its
strength or it might mean returned to its source. Like anyway we'll
see. Anyway, he had a real hard time resisting the tension and
the need to release
because it came at you know at that last at the critical
moment. ויפוזו זרועי ידיו. Vayaphozu zero'ei yadav. And his you know the
זרע zera here of his hands, the seed of his hands sort
of spread or scattered. נעץ אצבעותיו בקרקע Na'atz etzba'otav b'karka he put
his fingers into the ground to you know to sort of to
prevent him from doing from ejaculating. ויצא שכבת זרע מבין צפורני ידיו.
Veyatza shichvat zera mibein tzippornei yadav. And rather than he ejaculated the
semen had to go somewhere, so it came out of his fingers.
So which is a way of describing how impossible it is at
a certain point to actually resist, right? Once it gets to a
certain stage. So he used all of his strength and ultimately it
had to still come out but it came out in a different
way. מידי אביר יעקב, Midei avir Yaakov, from the power of יעקב.
Yaakov. מי גרם לו שיחקק על אבני אפוד Mi garam lo sheyichakek
al avnei ephod who caused him that ultimately his name would be
written on the אבני אפוד? avnei ephod? אלא אביר יעקב, Ella Avir
Yaakov, the strength of יעקב. Yaakov. משם רועה Misham ro'eh this plays
back about the רועה זונות. ro'eh zonot. From there he became a
shepherd of אבן ישראל, Even Yisrael, משם זכה ונעשה רועה, misham zachah
vena'aseh ro'eh, from there he merited and became a shepherd, שנאמר רועה
ישראל האזינה, shene'emar ro'eh Yisrael ha'azinah, shepherd of Israel hear, נוהג כצאן
יוסף noheig katzon Yosef being shepherd or led like the flock of
יוסף. Yosef. תניא Tanya we learned in a ברייתא, Baraita, just do
one more line. היה ראוי יוסף להוציא ממנו י"ב שבטים, Hayah ra'uy
Yosef l'hotzi mimenu yud-bet shevatim, you know what, we'll end right there.
Okay.